Good morning. So with today's דף daf we start a new מסכת
masechet and we begin תענית. Taanit. And now you can hold onto
the one volume you have; well, I don't know if you have
ArtScroll, the Steinsaltz, the Schottenstein. We're going to be going through all
of the remaining small מסכתות masechtot that are bundled in this one
volume: תענית, Taanit, מגילה, Megillah, מועד קטן, Moed Katan, and חגיגה. Chagigah.
So we'll be doing now we already sort of started with ראש
השנה, Rosh Hashanah, but about a מסכת masechet a month for four
more months until we finish until we finish מועד. Moed. And תענית,
Taanit,
as the title indicates, obviously focuses on the issues of fasting. And
but besides the fasting, which should be first of all when we
say fast, our initial thoughts are about what I would call the
historical fasts, the fasts to
commemorate tragedies in the past on particular days. These are actually ones
that are
reflected by the when the people come back
after the exile and they say, "Should we continue to fast like
we've been fasting, צום החמישי Tsom Ha-chamishi וצום השביעי ve-Tsom Ha-shivi-i וצום
העשירי?" ve-Tsom Ha-asiri? Should we continue to fast as we've been fasting
before? And the נביא Navi says back to them that they will
be these days will be לששון ולשמחה. le-sasson u-le-simcha. With the rebuilding
of a בית המקדש, Beit Ha-mikdash, these things that had been fast
days will return into days of rejoicing and so on. We actually
just discussed some of that in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah when we
discussed the issue of מגילת תענית. Megillat Taanit. So while on the
one hand those are that is something that
is very much indicated, a primary in our mindset when we think
about fast days, and indicated already like in the נביאים Neviim as
the first record that there were very particular days that they would
fast. Nevertheless, that's a very secondary concern to this מסכת. masechet. And
this מסכת masechet really is the issue is responding fasting as a
response to tragedy or impending tragedy, specifically around the issue of the
lack and absence of rain.
And as such, by the way, if one looks at the תפילה
tefilla of שלמה Shlomo when he's building the בית המקדש Beit Ha-mikdash
and he talks about why people will turn to God, one of
the central things that he says in his תפילה tefilla is if
there is no rain and they will direct their prayers to You
in this place, or he says, or if
there is a tragedy and there is locust and there is famine
and there is this, they will direct their prayers to You in
this place. This would be the common reason why people would pray
to God, because it's not raining and you're concerned that the whole
all the crops are going to go to waste and there'll be
famine in the year. If there's some other tragedy, if you're living
in an agricultural society, certainly people had the same types of concerns
we have about illness and so on, but the more recurring reason
why your life feels precarious and you're not certain about the future
and you turn to God is because of the things that are
happening with the agriculture, infestations
and so on, and also
the rain is the regular type of a thing as a regular
reason that you turn to God. And as such, it's important to
think about this מסכת masechet not only when we think about it,
not just as about fasting, but to think about it almost in
a counterpart in a way we'll sort of see this on the
first דף daf to like מסכת ברכות. Masechet Berachot. מסכת ברכות Masechet
Berachot is like fixed liturgy, right? So you have the שמע, Shema,
you have the שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. It's not responding to any
particular event that occurred. While to some degree the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh
Esrei is three times a day
because according to the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and
other hints that it's basically about the different places in which the
sun is, and sunrise it evokes a certain type of a feeling,
the sun is setting it evokes a different, night evokes a different
type of a feeling, nevertheless those are natural rhythms of the day
even if they're somehow responding to a different type of an emotional
state during in the morning, in the afternoon, and in the evening,
but it's basically a fixed type of a liturgy. To the degree
in ברכות Berachot you get a type of a liturgy or a
type of a religious response to more periodic occurrences or to more
immediate things that are occurring in response to the change of situation,
you get in the ברכות השבח. Birchot Ha-shevach. So like you see
the thunder and the lightning, you see the trees blossoming or just
something good happens and you say שהחיינו She-he-che-yanu and something bad happens
and you say ברוך דיין האמת. Baruch Dayan Ha-emet. That you get
at the very end of ברכות. Berachot. Here this may be in
some ways can be seen as picking up that theme, or I
would more say contrasting the basic liturgy, the fixed liturgy. And this
is the basic point about a religious response to what's occurring in
a person's life. Now obviously the central thing here is about the
rain and tragedy, it's about bad things, not good things, but it's
talking but in that way this מסכת masechet is very much
about it's very
focused on this type of a what it means to sort of
see God in the world or see God's see sort of absence
of God or God punishing
and sort of to the need to call out to God to
respond to that and to try to produce rain. pray for God's
kindness or bring or pray for God's more greater presence in the
world, and so this is really a מסכת Masechet that deals a
lot with the religious response to one's circumstances and to a very
type of a religious engagement with the world. I would say more
than any other מסכת Masechet which much more, I mean obviously our
entire, you know, life is religious, but it's much more tends to
be about ritual and structure, and, you know, fix, and this also
becomes fix, but it nevertheless is very much about a response to
seeing God's presence or feeling God's presence or absence in the world
and how one responds. And in that way, you know, I think
it's very important to think about what the basic theme of this
מסכת Masechet is and not to just automatically think oh, it's about
how you fast. I mean the fast is one profound response and
I think it is worth thinking about the idea about why is
it called מסכת תענית. Masechet Taanit. תענית Taanit is not mentioned in
the first משנה. Mishna. The first משנה Mishna is going to mention
aspects of the דאווענינג, davening, and one of the responses of course
when there's no rain, during the fast day is a whole separate
special set of prayers, right? So תפילות tefillot also change during the
fast day, but nevertheless it's the prayers you say during the fast
day and the primary way the nature of the day changes is
that the day becomes a fast day. But it does also do
something when we think about that as the dominant, what's the religious
response to absence of rain or to, you know, infestation or whatever,
you fast. You know, as opposed to say well, there's a couple
things you do, you fast, you pray, you do תשובה, teshuva, right?
So the dominance theme here becomes fasting and that also shapes a
particular perception. But again, I think it's important to start by just
saying this is not just like how do we do various תעניות.
taaniyot. You know, it fundamentally starts with this issue about a religious
engagement in the world, you know, in a sense of a religious
response to things that are happening to us. Yeah, you had a
question?
Just
I can understand a lot of responses to tragedy. Why is the
religious response to tragedy fasting? Fasting is self-denial so what's the connection
between?
Right, so that is an excellent question. And again, if you go
back to like I said like the prayer by שלמה, Shlomo, where
he dedicates the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you know, there he talks
about the primary reason people will pray will be because of these
terrible things and they'll direct their prayer, right? So in a sense
you had prayer by itself, although there again it was much more
שבח shevach than bad things. To the degree it was bad, it
was ברוך דיין האמת Baruch Dayan HaEmet which is about the past,
not about the praying for the future, you know. So there you
had it in ברכות. Berachot. So again, that's exactly the point I
want us to be thinking about, that, you know, framing it the
way I did it raises the question, so if that's what this
is about, why is תענית taanit the dominant theme and what is
the religious value of תענית? taanit? So keep that question in mind,
that's a question I want us to be reflecting on as we
go through the מסכת. Masechet. Okay, was there another question? No? Okay,
so let's take a look. Let me here maybe just take one
more second and just read the פסוקים psukim by שלמה Shlomo that
I've been referring to, if I can find them quickly, and then
just to give you a sense how this is a theme that
plays out.
It's a huge chapter.
I know. What פרק perek is it? Do you remember?
מלכים ב ח? Melachim Bet Chet?
Yeah, thank you. Actually it's about 75 פסוקים. psukim.
No, מלכים ב Melachim Bet is too late. מלכים
א?
Melachim Aleph?
מלכים א
פרק ח.
Melachim Aleph Perek
Chet.
Oh you're right, you're right. So listen to this, okay, here's what
שלמה Shlomo says why people will pray as he's dedicating the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. He says: ופנית אל תפלת עבדך ואל תחנתו השם
אלקי לשמע אל הרנה ואל התפלה אשר עבדך מתפלל לפניך היום. להיות
עיניך פתחות אל הבית הזה לילה ויום,
ufanita el tfillat avdecha veel tchinato Hashem Elokei lishmoa el harina veel
hatfilla asher avdecha mitpallel lefanecha hayom. lihyot einecha ptuchot el
habayit haze lalla vayom, right? אשר יתפלל עבדך אל המקום הזה, asher
yitpallel avdecha el hamakom haze,
so you'll always be hearing the prayers. ושמעת אל תחנת עבדך ועמך
ישראל אשר יתפללו. vshamaata el tchinat avdecha veamcha Yisrael asher yitpallelu.
Now what are they going to pray? את אשר יחטא איש לרעהו
ונשא בו אלה להאלתו ובא אלה לפני מזבחך בבית הזה. et asher
yecheta ish lereahu venasa bo ala leaaloto uva ala lifnei mizbachacha babayit
haze. Okay,
so first of all somebody gets a curse so you're going to
be responsive to that. Then right after that בהנגף עמך ישראל לפני
אויב אשר יחטאו לך ושבו אליך והודו את שמך. behinagef amcha Yisrael
lifnei oyev asher yechetu lach vshavu elecha vehodu et shemecha. ואתה תשמע
השמים וסלחת. veata tishma hashamayim vsalachta. בהעצר השמים ולא יהיה מטר, beheatzer
hashamayim velo yihye matar, ואתה תשמע השמים וסלחת. veata tishma hashamayim vsalachta.
רעב כי יהיה בארץ דבר כי יהיה שדפון ירקון ארבה חסיל כי
יהיה כי יצר לו איבו בארץ שעריו, raav ki yihye baaretz dever
ki yihye shidafon yerakon arbe chasil ki yihye ki yetzar lo oyvo
bearetz shearav, כל תפלה כל תחנה אשר תהיה לכל האדם לכל עמך
ישראל אשר ידעון איש נגע לבבו ופרש כפיו אל הבית הזה. kol
tfillat kol tchina asher tihye lechol haadam lechol amcha Yisrael asher yidun
ish nega levavo ufarash kapav el habayit haze.
So of those things it's basically tragedy. Rain, lack of rain is
one of them but all the other types of things that could
happen: רעב, raav, שדפון, shidafon, חסיל, chasil, right, infestation, famine. So that
is all about prayer. What in our מסכת Masechet what that becomes
is the basis for תעניות. taaniyot.
Yes, just to say that the refrain in what you
read was וסלחת. vsalachta. So tragedy is being conceptualized biblically as the
punishment for some type of human shortcoming or sin, so there's a
requirement for a forgiveness as a result.
I thank
you very much, that's an excellent point and that's also a theme
that we're going to see right, it's not just like a prayer
for compassion like we need you, please give it to us, but
a sense that if this is happening, it's because of sin. And
then the issue of fasting becomes is to connect, you know, is
in our minds, which connects to is that related to יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur? To what degree is fasting something of a way of,
you know, of
either תשובה teshuva or a way of look, we're punishing ourselves and
therefore we've been suffered, so therefore we should be forgiven. But I
think Dov makes the excellent point that yes, it's prayer but also
when there's prayer, when there's a sense of, you know, of tragedy
or bad things, there's a sense of sin and a need to
be forgiven. And that's also something we have to think about as
we go through this מסכת. masechet. Yes.
Agricultural productivity specifically mentioning in the שמע Shema is being a function
of our actions.
Excellent! And that we're going to see on the first דף. daf.
So that's enough for הקדמה, hakdama, but again, these are really important
themes to be thinking about so that we don't just sort of
go into the mindset of fasting. Okay, so let's take a look
at the first משנה. mishna. מאימתי Me'ematai opens the same way ברכות
Berachot opens. מאימתי מזכירין גבורות גשמים? Me'ematai mazkirim gevurot geshamim? When do
you start mentioning the power of the rain? משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם.
Mashiv haruach umorid hageshem. So רבי אליעזר אומר: מיום טוב הראשון של
חג Rabbi Eliezer omer miyom tov harishon shel chag. starting on the
first day of חג. chag. The simple sense of חג, chag, חג
chag by itself means סוכות, Sukkot, because that's a period of rain
as we know, as we'll see. You wave לולב lulav and אתרוג,
etrog, you do the ניסוך המים. nisuch hamayim. רבי יהושע אומר: Rabbi
Yehoshua omer: מיום טוב האחרון של חג mi'yom tov ha'acharon shel chag
no, only on the last day of חג. chag. Now that would
sound like it means the seventh of סוכות, Sukkot, it's possible he
means after the last day, starting after סוכות Sukkot is over on
שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. אמר לו רבי יהושע, Amar lo Rabbi Yehoshua,
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said to him, הואיל ואין הגשמים אלא סימן
קללה בחג ho'il v'ein hageshamim ela siman kelala bechag since the rain
is really only a sign of curse on the חג. chag. Why
does he say that? Either presumably because of the משנה mishna in
סוכה Sukkah which says that if you, if it rains on סוכות,
Sukkot, it is,
it's like a person who is coming to serve the water to
his master, and the master takes the jug of water and throws
it on the servant. So we're trying to sit in the סוכה
Sukkah and do a מצוה, mitzvah, and God is driving us out
of the סוכה Sukkah with the rain. So it is a סימן
siman of displeasure if it happens, if rain happens on סוכות, Sukkot,
of God's displeasure with us. למה הוא מזכיר? Lama hu mazkir? Why
would you mention משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם mashiv haruach umorid hageshem if
you don't want, you don't want it to rain yet on סוכות?
Sukkot? So אמר לו רבי אליעזר, amar lo Rabbi Eliezer, so רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said back, אף אני לא אמרתי לשאול אלא להזכיר.
af ani lo amarti lishol ela lehazkir. I didn't say to start
asking, you don't start saying ותן טל ומטר לברכה, v'tein tal u'matar
livracha, you don't start requesting from God that it should rain. You
only מזכיר, mazkir,
you mention that God brings the rain. You're mentioning the powers of
God, but you're not, it's not a specific request that it begin
now. משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם בעונתו, Mashiv haruach umorid hageshem be'onoto, you
cause the wind to blow and the rain to fall in its
right time. By the way, this whole thing of משיב הרוח, mashiv
haruach, you know, we sort of gloss over that. I was reading
something last night about how that this is very true in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael that before the serious rains comes, they're preceded with
very heavy winds. I don't know, but anyway, something to look into.
So אמר לו, amar lo, so he said, look, I'm not asking
for it to come now, I'm just mentioning it. So אמר לו,
amar lo, so רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said back to him, אם
כן im kein if that's true,
לעולם יהא מזכיר. le'olam yehei mazkir. So you should mention it the
whole year, why do you only mention it now? Obviously you're mentioning
it now because you want it now, but if you're saying it
now because you want it now, then you shouldn't say it until
after סוכות Sukkot is over. Okay, and we don't have a response,
we'll see a response in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
So now אין שואלין את הגשמים ein sho'alin et hageshamim since we
mentioned the idea that there's not only mentioning the rain but there's
asking ותן טל ומטר. v'tein tal u'matar.
That you only do אלא סמוך לגשמים ela samuch lageshamim near when
you actually is the time of rain. So even you don't even
do that even right after סוכות, Sukkot, you only start really requesting
it when the time is coming when you actually, when
you're expecting it to rain. And we'll see what that time is
later. רבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi Yehuda omer. So this is a little
bit strange, the order of the משנה, mishna, because we're mentioning משיב
הרוח ומוריד הגשם, mashiv haruach umorid hageshem, then we mention אין שואלין,
ein sho'alin, the issue about שואלין, sho'alin, ותן טל ומטר, v'tein tal
u'matar, and then we go back to finishing up the discussion of
משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם. mashiv haruach umorid hageshem. We have a brief
mention of ותן טל ומטר v'tein tal u'matar without expanding it, and
now we're going back to משיב הרוח. mashiv haruach. Okay. רבי יהודה
אומר העובר לפני התיבה ביום טוב האחרון של חג האחרון מזכיר הראשון
אינו מזכיר. Rabbi Yehuda omer: ha'over lifnei hateiva beyom tov ha'acharon shel
chag, ha'acharon mazkir, harishon eino mazkir. Here's when you do say משיב
הרוח mashiv haruach and when you don't. The person who goes before
the תיבה, teiva, meaning the בעל תפילה, ba'al tefilla, the שליח ציבור,
shliach tzibbur, the last day of חג. chag. So this means the
last day and it's יום טוב, yom tov, meaning it's not סוכות,
Sukkot, it's שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. So האחרון מזכיר. ha'acharon mazkir. The
second person, the בעל מוסף ba'al musaf says משיב הרוח. mashiv haruach.
הראשון, harishon, the בעל שחרית ba'al shacharit אינו מזכיר. eino mazkir. So
you say it at מוסף, musaf, you start saying it at
מוסף musaf in שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. ביום טוב הראשון של פסח
הראשון מזכיר. Beyom tov harishon shel Pesach, harishon mazkir. The בעל שחרית
ba'al shacharit says it. האחרון אינו מזכיר. ha'acharon eino mazkir. The בעל
מוסף Baal Musaf stops saying it. Okay, so this is exactly what
we do. We say משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv haruach umorid hageshem
from מוסף Musaf of שמיני עצרת Shmini Atzeret through שחרית Shacharit of
פסח. Pesach. Now is he really what he's really doing is a
subtly different position than רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. First of all, you
don't know by רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua when he when you stop
saying משיב הרוח. Mashiv haruach. So he clarifies you stop saying on
the first day of פסח. Pesach. It's also subtly different because רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says you start saying it after the last day
of סוכות. Sukkot. So according to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua presumably you
say it the night of שמיני עצרת Shmini Atzeret or maybe שחרית
Shacharit of שמיני עצרת, Shmini Atzeret, whereas רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
creating a much clearer structure. It's from מוסף Musaf until the next
מוסף. Musaf. No, you don't start saying it the morning of שמיני
עצרת, Shmini Atzeret, you start it the מוסף Musaf of שמיני עצרת
Shmini Atzeret and that goes all the way up to but not
including the מוסף Musaf of פסח. Pesach. And we'll see why in
the גמרא. Gemara. So again, this is the first משנה, Mishnah, it's
pretty much all about saying משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם. Mashiv haruach umorid
hageshem. Nothing bad has happened yet. This is a normal year. You're
just expecting things to happen God-willing normally. You're not even yet at
the point of asking yet, you just mentioned God's power of משיב
הרוח ומוריד הגשם. Mashiv haruach umorid hageshem. Right, no anxiety has yet
come into the picture and the only question is when do you
start. The only reason for the insertion of אין שואלין אלא סמוך
לגשמים, ein shoalin ela samuch legeshamim, the asking of ותן טל ומטר,
ten tal umatar, since we're going to expand on that in a
later משנה, Mishnah, is for the sake of clarifying the debate of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua because רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua sort of said they were discussing, "Hey, you know, you
don't ask, why are you mentioning it's not the right time?" and
he's saying, "Well, there's a difference between mentioning and asking for it."
So the משנה Mishnah sort of clarified the asking for it clearly
happens later and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying, "I'm not yet
talking about asking for it. That I admit is going to happen
later. I'm talking about the mentioning of it." So it's a little
bit discordant that one line. We're going to really expand the idea
of ותן טל ומטר, ten tal umatar, שואלים, shoalim, but it was
brought here to give a clarification to what the issues are at
stake here in terms of the מזכירים, mazkirim, yes.
We do have in this language also a Mishnaic paradigm for different
types of prayer. In other words, we call some types of prayers
בקשה, bakashah, that's שואלים. shoalim. Right. Right. They're using the language of
להזכיר lehazkir as to conceptualize the function of prayer as to articulate
a consciousness of God. Like a...
okay, so that's a nice idea. I mean, for our own consciousness,
right. But שבח shevach is more the classic and that's exactly the
difference that משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv haruach umorid hageshem is in
the first three which are seen as שבח shevach and ותן טל
ומטר לברכה ten tal umatar livracha is in the middle ברכות brachot
which are about שואלים shoalim and בקשה. bakashah. Right.
Exactly. Exactly. Right, it's a very good point. Let's take a look
at the גמרא, Gemara, yes.
Why is he using גשם geshem in one phrase and מטר matar
in the other?
Oh,
so that's a very good point.
I have to think about that, get back to you about that.
I mean, the פסוקים psukim have גשם, geshem, right? ונתתי גשמיכם בעתם.
Venatati gishmeichem beitam. Does it have
מטר? matar? מטר השמים, matar hashamayim, yes, לתת מטר ארצכם בעתו. latet
matar artzechem beito. I don't know exactly what the whether there's a,
you know, a different connotation between מטר matar and גשם. geshem.
I mean, it doesn't say מטר. matar. I was saying when it
says מזכיר, mazkir, the מזכיר mazkir is ותן טל ומטר לברכה. ten
tal umatar livracha. That's what we say in our שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh
Esrei. We say ותן טל ומטר. ten tal umatar. It's not in
the משנה. Mishnah. But you're right, when in the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh
Esrei we say משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv haruach umorid hageshem and
then when we ask for it, no, it's not in the משנה,
Mishnah, but when we ask for it, the מזכירים mazkirim is מוריד
הגשם. morid hageshem. The שואלים shoalim is ותן טל ומטר לברכה. ten
tal umatar livracha. So you're right, in the שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei.
In the משנה, Mishnah, it's referred to as גשם geshem in both
cases. Alright, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. תנא
היכא קאי דקתני מאימתי? Tanna heicha kai diktani me'eimatai? Where what is
the frame of reference of the תנא Tanna that he's saying what
time do we begin saying, which means that you assume that you
already know you're supposed to say it? How do you know you're
supposed to say it before you can ask when you say? The
first גמרא Gemara in ברכות Berachot has the same question. The משנה
Mishnah opens, you know, when you say שמע Shema in the evening,
and the גמרא Gemara says, "How do you know you're supposed to
say שמע Shema altogether before you can ask when you say?" So
it's the same question here. Where what's your point of reference that
you're already assuming you say it that you're asking when do you
begin saying? So the גמרא Gemara says תנא התם קאי דקתני. Tanna
hatam kai diktani. It goes it's going back to ברכות. Berachot. In
ברכות Berachot we say מזכירין גבורות גשמים בתחיית המתים. mazkirin gevurot geshamim
bitchiyat hametim. You mention the power of the גשם geshem in the
תחיית המתים tchiyat hametim in the second ברכה, bracha, מחיה מתים. mechayeh
metim. ושואלין, veshoalin, you have the request for it, so there's again
that language of מזכירין mazkirin and שואלין, shoalin, בברכת השנים bevirkat hashanim
in the ברכה bracha of the years, right, ברך עלינו את השנה
הזאת, barech aleinu et hashana hazot, right, והבדלה בחונן הדעת, vehavdala bechonen
hadaat, and you mention and הבדלה Havdala when it's מוצאי שבת Motzaei
Shabbat or מוצאי יום טוב Motzaei Yom Tov is in, you know,
the fourth ברכה bracha of חונן הדעת. chonen hadaat. So it mentions
the different types of insertions you make in שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei.
That's a משנה Mishnah there in ברכות. Berachot. וקתני, vekatni, so since
we mentioned way back in ברכות Berachot that you'll add you'll add
various things in the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei around the rain, so
this משנה's Mishnah coming to clarify that משנה. Mishnah. קתני מאימתי מזכירין
גבורות גשמים, katni me'eimatai mazkirin gevurot geshamim, so therefore this משנה's Mishnah
coming to clarify it.
So the גמרא Gemara says... That's true, it comes to clarify a
משנה Mishna way back in ברכות, Brachot, וליתני התם! velitnei hatam! So
talk about it over there when you're supposed to make those insertions.
מאי שנא דשבקיה הכא? Mai shna deshvakia hacha? Why are you waiting
until now? אלא Ela rather, תנא מראש השנה סליק. Tanna me'Rosh Hashanah
salik. He's departing from the מסכת Masechet of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
like we just did. You just finished learning ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
which is the מסכת Masechet that comes before this. דתנן Detnan and
what did we teach in ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? ובחג נידונים על
המים Uvechag nidonim al hamayim that on סוכות Sukkot is the time
that we're judged for water. So if we're judged for water, you
have to discuss how do you respond to that fact that it's
a, that it's a judgment and that we want the,
you know, we want to pray for it to be good rains
for the coming year. ואיידי דתני ובחג נידונים על המים, Ve'aidi detani
uvechag nidonim al hamayim, so if it's, so just if, once we
taught that, תנא נמי מאימתי מזכירין גבורות גשמים. Tanna nami me'eimatai mazkirin
gevurot geshamim. So we're going to start talking about mentioning משיב הרוח
ומוריד הגשם Mashiv haruach umorid hagashem as a way of responding to
the fact that it is the time of rain and the time
of דין Din about, about rain. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, if that's true, וליתני מאימתי מזכירין על הגשמים. Velitnei me'eimatai mazkirin
al hageshamim. I'm sorry, וליתני
מאימתי מזכירין על הגשמים. Velitnei me'eimatai mazkirin al hageshamim. Why does it
say גבורות גשמים? Gevurot geshamim? Just say when do you start mentioning
rain? What's the use of the word גבורות? Gevurot?
מאי גבורות? Mai Gvurot? What does it mean by the powers of
rain? אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan מפני שיורדין בגבורה mipnei she'yordin
bigvurah because they come down through God's might. שנאמר Shene'emar how do
we see this? So now we're going to have a whole string
of פסוקים Psukim to get us to the idea that the idea
of גבורה Gevurah is connected to the idea of rain.
שנאמר Shene'emar the verse says עושה גדולות ואין חקר Oseh gedolot ve'ein
cheker God does wonders without understanding, you know, beyond comprehension, ונפלאות עד
אין מספר Veniflaot ad ein mispar and wondrous things without number. וכתיב
Uchtiv הנותן מטר על פני ארץ ושולח מים על פני חוצות. Hanoten
matar al pnei aretz veshloach mayim al pnei chutzot. God gives the
rain on the face of the earth and sends water towards the
fields. מאי משמע? Mai mashma? So where do you get from that
the idea that rain is associated with גבורה? Gevurah? אמר רבה בר
שילה Amar Rabba bar Shila אתיא חקר חקר מבריאתו של עולם. Atya
cheker cheker mibriato shel olam. So there you have that God's greatnesses
are described as beyond comprehension, אין חקר. ein cheker. And in somewhere
the same context, although if you look at the side, it's four
פרקים Prakim earlier, but okay, somewhere the same context we have a
mention of rain. So somehow rain there is connected with the idea
of being beyond comprehension. All right, so let's keep on going.
וכתיב התם Uchtiv hatam now that we have this word אין חקר,
ein cheker, it says over there in ישעיהו Yeshayahu הלוא ידעת אם
לא שמעת אלוהי עולם ה' בורא קצות הארץ לא ייעף ולא ייגע
אין חקר לתבונתו. Halo yadata im lo shamata elohei olam Hashem borei
katzot ha'aretz lo yi'af velo yiga ein cheker litvunato. God is the,
you know, God of the world,
creates the extremities of the land,
is not weary and does not tire. אין חקר לתבונתו, Ein cheker
litvunato, there is no understanding, it's beyond comprehension God's wisdom, God's understanding.
וכתיב Uchtiv and it says, מכין הרים בכוחו נאזר בגבורה. Machin harim
bekocho ne'ezar bigvurah. So that פסוק pasuk in ישעיהו Yeshayahu is about
בריאת העולם, Briat ha'olam, בורא קצות הארץ. borei katzot ha'aretz. So the
act of בריאת העולם Briat ha'olam is connected with the idea of
beyond comprehension, אין חקר. ein cheker. And another פסוק pasuk in תהילים
Tehillim which talks about בריאת העולם Briat ha'olam says מכין הרים בכוחו
נאזר בגבורה, Machin harim bekocho ne'ezar bigvurah, God smites the mountains with
His strength, He girds Himself with גבורה. Gevurah. So it's a very
stringing of פסוקים. Psukim. We have פסוקים Psukim in ישעיהו Yeshayahu that
talks about בריאת העולם Briat ha'olam which is beyond
comprehension. We have a פסוק pasuk in תהילים Tehillim that in the
context of בריאת העולם Briat ha'olam is associated with an idea of
גבורה Gevurah of God's power. So now בריאת העולם Briat ha'olam is
associated with God's power. Then we have פסוקים Psukim in איוב Iyov
that talk about the rain and connect the rain with beyond comprehension,
so we import the idea of God's גבורה Gevurah to now apply
to the regular about the rain. It's very convoluted to get this
idea of rain going on here. But what are we doing here?
תוספות Tosafot by the way says there's a lot of other verbs
that are used here, כוח, Koach, you know,
בכוחו, bekocho,
נאזר. ne'ezar. Anyway, so if you take a look תוספות Tosafot basically
says the real reason we're focusing on this word גבורה. Gevurah. If
you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, וכתיב מכין הרים בכוחו נאזר
בגבורה. Uchtiv machin harim bekocho ne'ezar bigvurah. So he goes on and
he says there's a lot of other things. אכן יש להקשות, Achen
yesh lehakshot, the line starts with the word להקשות, lehakshot, about eight
lines until the lines get wide. אמאי נקט גבורה טפי מכוח? Amai
nakat Gvurah tfei mikoach? וכמו כן הוה ליה למימר מזכירין כוח גשמים.
Uchmo chen hava lei lemeimar mazkirin koach geshamim. So he says, he
says, אומנם, Omnam, the last two lines of this תוספות, Tosafot, משום
דהברכה מתחלת בגבורה והכי נקט גבורה, mishum dehabracha matchala bigvurah vehachi nakat
gvurah, which is really the reason that everybody says, which is that
it's גבורות גשמים Gevurot geshamim because it is, how does the ברכה
Bracha begin? Well we mention it in אתה גיבור לעולם ה'. Atah
gibor le'olam Hashem. So it's mentioned in the ברכה Bracha of גבורות.
Gevurot. We also call it the ברכה Bracha of תחיית המתים, Techiat
hametim, but it is the ברכה Bracha of גבורות, Gevurot, so we
are calling this גבורות גשמים. Gevurot geshamim. So all the גמרא Gemara
is saying is that's an appropriate term to use by גשמים, Geshamim,
the concept of גבורה, Gevurah, but it occurs in the ברכה Bracha
of גבורות Gevurot which is really why it is called that. Now
I want to say some things about the גמרא Gemara we just
read. First of all... the question of are we responding to the
משנה Mishna in ברכות Berachot which says when do you make insertions
in שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei are we responding to the משנה Mishna
in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah that says that says
it's a time of a יום הדין Yom HaDin now first of
all just an interesting sort of
bibliographic point רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot say what we'd rather be
referring to ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah which is in the same סדר
Seder סדר מועד Seder Moed as opposed to ברכות Berachot which is
in סדר זרעים Seder Zeraim they don't say the more obvious thing
which is as we know by having done the דף יומי Daf
Yomi that ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah came right before this מסכת Masechet
so it's not just it's in the same סדר Seder it like
immediately preceded this מסכת Masechet you know and often the גמרא Gemara
says well this is coming because of the immediately preceding מסכת Masechet
so I haven't done any research on this I don't know the
scholarship on it but I do wonder if our like organization that
we have like ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah יומא Yoma סוכה Sukkah which
has been reorganized in order to make it chronological right first you
have ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah then יום כיפור Yom Kippur if that
was already the organization that was in the time of the ראשונים
Rishonim because if they had the organization of the original organization of
the משנה Mishna like we know by having done the דף יומי
Daf Yomi רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot would have said well of
course you want to refer back to ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah it
was the immediately previous מסכת Masechet not just it's the same סדר
Seder that's just a bibliographic point but back to this issue of
what's our frame of reference you know in a way this raises
this question about and it can be seen as the debate of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua right so רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says you don't start mentioning משיב הרוח Mashiv HaRuach
until you want the rain so for רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua משיב
הרוח Mashiv HaRuach is a prelude to asking about it but it's
all about getting around to asking for it so maybe you say
משיב הרוח Mashiv HaRuach a little bit earlier you say it שמיני
עצרת Shemini Atzeret you don't start asking for it until you know
מרחשון MarCheshvan or December 4th or 5th if you're in חוץ לארץ
Chutz LaAretz but the way you build up to asking for it
is first you start praising God משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv HaRuach
Umorid HaGeshem and then we're going to get around to asking for
it but it's all a prelude to asking that's what רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua says right so you don't start it unless you're ready
for it whereas רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no maybe it's not
related yet to asking you know or maybe if it is a
prelude it can come before you're ready to ask but maybe it's
not even related to asking maybe it's you know if it's the
time when rain starts coming so maybe you start mentioning this as
the relevant thing of this time is to acknowledge God as the
power of bringing the rain and it's not necessarily in the context
of a request so in a way that relates to the question
of are you anchored in ברכות Berachot or are you anchored in
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah in ברכות Berachot when it says for example
that you say הבדלה Havdalah בחונן הדעת b'Chonen HaDa'at when you say
הבדלה Havdalah are you asking for anything you're not asking for anything
you're making insertions in שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei as is appropriate for
the day or for the time of the year so the appropriate
insertion in the rainy season is משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv HaRuach
Umorid HaGeshem it doesn't have anything to do with a request it's
the thing we're supposed to be mentioning during this time that's like
that's one way of thinking about it maybe that's רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer who says you can start saying it already at the beginning
of סוכות Sukkot whereas if your sense is the reason we're talking
about rain is because we're נידונים על המים nidonim al hamayim and
that gets us to the whole point of תענית Taanit and we
want to make sure that we get the rain and it's a
big concern then the whole mention of משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv
HaRuach Umorid HaGeshem is a buildup to that well that's in the
context of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah of נידונים על המים nidonim al
hamayim and that maybe is רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua point don't start
mentioning the rain unless you're ready to have it because the whole
point of mentioning it is the lead-in to the asking of it
okay so that's a way I think a way of seeing the
debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua in
terms of this initial question of what's our frame of reference yes
Joe
I have a very small question about תוספות Tosafot are you suggesting
that when תוספות Tosafot
introduces their comment with אי נמי ee nami
that
I should read that as their primary
bottom-line position
no for תוספות Tosafot אי נמי ee nami is an equivalent but
I'm just saying that almost everybody assumes that that second answer is
the obvious answer you know and the real and the better answer
right I wasn't saying in
תוספות Tosafot right right but I'm telling
you with תוספות Tosafot it's a real answer now I want to
say another thing about this issue about גבורות Gevurot and this is
an important thing to think about about משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv
HaRuach Umorid HaGeshem in general so A the idea of גבורה Gevura
and the linking to מעשה בראשית Maaseh Bereishit also here is an
important question right by linking this to the idea of גבורה Gevura
and מעשה בראשית Maaseh Bereishit it also takes it out of the
framework of like oh please we need the rain and it's a
lead-in to בקשה Bakashah it's part of you know just appreciating the
wonders of creation and God's power in creating the world and when
we sort of see the rain it just evokes for us again
God's power in nature and it's the part like it's a religious
response that's not in the context of you know of the fact
that we need this thing to happen and that it's a lead-in
to the request again it's a type of a more ברכות Berachot
orientation and a more general שבח Shevach and not just a lead-in
to the ותן טל ומטר v'ten tal u'matar or lead-in to the
בקשה Bakashah so although it was very convoluted how the גמרא Gemara
here got גבורה gevurah associated with rain, but again, I think by
framing it in the context of בריאת העולם, briat haolam, it is
important in terms of frame of of creating our frame of reference.
One other thing I do want to say about this is and
this is worth mentioning. I think this is a point I read
in ראובן קימלמן, Reuven Kimelman, it's his argument so if you don't
like it don't blame me. But you know it's quite fascinating, well
you know what I'm going to hold off on the point until
we read the next line because it ties in more to the
next line we're going to see. Yes?
Steinsaltz mentions
that מאירי Meiri had a different order of the tractates but he
doesn't say what it was.
Okay, thank you. So now let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. It says like this. Okay. Now. ומנלן
דבתפילה? U-minalan de-btfillah?
How do you know you're supposed to say משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם
Mashiv haruach umorid hagashem in prayer, that it belongs in prayer? So
now you could have said, I saw somebody who commented well why
don't we say like it says by שלמה, Shlomo, if there's no
rain they'll pray to You. But the point here is no, that's
if there's like a tragedy or an impending tragedy. There's no rain.
How do you know you say it just on an ongoing basis?
Even when everything is going in the right way, that you're supposed
to mention God's power in bringing the rain. להזכיר. Lahazkir. דתניא, D'tanya,
we taught in the ברייתא, Beraita, לאהבה את השם אלקיכם ולעבדו בכל
לבבכם. Le'ahava et Hashem Elokeichem ule'avdo bechol levavchem.
So somebody mentioned this right, the connection of מצוות mitzvot to rain.
איזו היא עבודה שבלב? Eizehu avodah shebalev? Which is the עבודה avodah
in the heart, ולעבדו בכל לבבכם, le'avdo bechol levavchem, so in your
heart? הוי אומר זו תפילה. Hevei omer zo tfillah. It's prayer. That's
an important idea about prayer that it's described as עבודה שבלב, avodah
shebalev, service of the heart. But that's not something I'm going to
unpack fully now. But ולעבדו בכל לבבכם le'avdo bechol levavchem is prayer.
וכתיב בתריה, Uch'tiv batreh, ונתתי מטר ארצכם בעתו יורה ומלקוש. venatati matar
artzechem be'ito yoreh umalkosh.
I will give the rain in its time, the early rain and
the late rain. So you see the idea of God giving the
rain is connected to serving God in prayer and therefore we should
be mentioning it in prayer. Now this I think, by the way,
again also noting the idea of that it's not just when bad
things happen and calling out to God because there's a tragedy is
again extremely important in terms of appreciating like the religious mindset that
I think חז"ל Chazal were aiming at and which I think is
more true, you know, in the time when they were so dependent
on the vicissitudes of nature. You know, somebody once said the reason
that it's so hard in high school for the kids to get
into דאווענינג davening is because you're asking them to pray for things
they don't need in a language they don't understand to a God
they don't believe in. It's always so detailed.
Anyway,
so the point is, you know, if you are living in that
cultural society, you are, I don't know, but it's quite possible depending
on maybe how successful you are and where it is that you're
living, but it's quite possible that sense of
precariousness about your general, you know, situation in life and your sense
of dependency, you know, we might feel precarious now, but it's like
where am I going to get a job, I might get fired,
and it doesn't sort of point us to God necessarily. But if
your precariousness has to do with the natural event and rain, and
think about it, rain comes from above, right, and comes down from
above and it gives life, you know, that sense of dependency on
God for our life and our sustenance is much more hopefully in
the forefront. And therefore the idea that not just when bad things
are happening, but לעבדו בכל לבבכם le'avdo bechol levavchem to serve God
with your whole heart means that acknowledgment of you do מצוות mitzvot
ונתתי גשמיכם. venatati gishmeichem. So the way almost you reflect, you know,
this serving of God with your heart is a constant acknowledgment about
God is the one who is providing rain, our dependency on rain,
our dependency on God, this is tied into our living a life
of מצוות mitzvot and doing the right things, right? That's like a
profound religious mindset. Right? You're constantly conscious about how your life of
of following God and doing the מצוות, mitzvot, you know, is you
know makes you know determines whether you'll be God will be providing
for you and you'll be getting rain and is part of, you
know, and and so it's it's something that sort of really I
think is very very powerful. It's not just a tiny point like,
oh, it says rain and it says תפילה, tfillah, so we should
mention rain in תפילה. tfillah. I think, you know, again the fact
that rain is dependent on מצוות mitzvot and that the number one
like, you know, the basic response to מצוות mitzvot that the תורה
Torah says is rain, right? If you do the מצוות mitzvot you
get rain, if you don't you don't. So that's like that's like
shows how much this is the very essence of of life is
having the rain and the so if you really believe that, right?
So that's very powerful then everything you do matters and is going
to determine whether you will be provided for or not and whether
there'll be rain or not and then therefore that's reflected in your
religious mindset of your תפילה tfillah and your prayers of בכל לבבכם
bechol levavchem are reflecting that type of an ongoing mindset. So I
think that again that's very powerful in terms of thinking about the
religious mindset that is at work here and it's not just a
like a hint, oh, you mention it in rain, you mention it
in דאווענינג. davening. That this just like again reflects this pervasive this
very thoroughgoing religious mindset. Okay, yeah.
Yes, to the question of is this where the service of the
heart and prayer is first mentioned?
Yeah, it's not here. I mean, it occurs, no, it only here
comes up in many places, but like in מדרשי תנאים Midrashei Tannaim
I think in the ספרי Sifrei and so on, it's you know
it's an earlier Tannaitic source. But this is definitely one of the
mentions of it. Yeah.
And the other question is for rain, in physical location like in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael rain is coming from above. Other locations, Egypt
or maybe Babylon where the water is coming through the
rivers, flooding. Right. So is there a different So I think there
is.
And I think, you know like the פסוקים psukim say, like when
it says that ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael לא
כארץ מצרים היא, lo k'eretz Mitzrayim hee, right, this is dependent on
rain. עיני השם אלוקיך בה מראשית השנה ועד אחרית שנה. einei Hashem
Elokecha bah mereshit hashanah v'ad acharit shanah. So the fact that it's
dependent on rain shifts profoundly. If you have a predictable Nile that
floods, then it's not the same degree of this precariousness and dependence
on God. If you don't know whether it'll be raining, and again
the just geographic, you know just sort of physically the rain is
coming from the light source coming from above, it creates a very
profound different religious mindset.
Right?
I think that that's absolutely true. So the contrast to מצרים Mitzrayim
and the context of therefore God is looking at Israel and determining
whether it's, you know whether it's going to rain, and that there's
involvement of God, and if you do the מצוות mitzvot you'll get
rain and if not, not. I mean right, that's like the theology
that runs throughout ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Right. And they desperately needed
it, right.
That's true. It's a different relationship.
But that is true. Right, but it's not, I don't think it
leads to as much of the same type of religious mindset that
the גמרא Gemara is talking about. Right. You know like I said,
you might get fired from your job, but that doesn't mean that
you're thinking about it in terms of God, right? So there are
bad things that can happen, but are you orienting towards God or
not? So yes, so again, all of this is very clear and
very much the religious theology, right? It's all going to be determined
by your מצוות, mitzvot, it's all about God and God's connection to
the land, and therefore the idea that it's central to thing to
be mentioned in prayer, right, on an ongoing basis, you know at
least during the time when it's relevant, you know is therefore, and
again, this is not just about praying for it in terms of
like because it might not happen, it's about that ongoing religious mindset.
Okay, so now we have two things mentioned about the rain. Number
one, the relationship to בריאת העולם briat ha'olam and גבורה, gevurah, and
number two, this aspect about the ongoing sense of מצוות mitzvot and
their connection to rain and your religious connection sort of to God.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay. אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, says רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. ג' מפתחות בידו
של הקדוש ברוך הוא. Gimmel maftechot beyado shel haKadosh Baruch Hu. And
this I think heightens this point. By the way, it's interesting to
note that you get a lot of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in
the first פרק perek and a lot of תנאים, Tannaim, a lot
of אמוראים Amoraim from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, much more than אמוראים
Amoraim from בבל. Bavel. And again, this might have something to do
with the reality of the need for rain and so on. So
that's just worth noticing. Okay, so God said there are three keys,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said there are three keys given in the
hands of God שלא נמסרו ביד שליח, shelo nimsru beyad shaliach, that
God doesn't give over to any person. God directly controls them. ואלו
הן, V'eilu hen, these are they: מפתח של גשמים, mafteach shel geshamim,
the key of rain, ומפתח של חיה, umafteach shel chaya, the key
of childbirth, ומפתח של תחיית המתים, umafteach shel techiyat hameitim, and the
key of resurrection. מפתח של גשמים, Mafteach shel geshamim, the one of
rain, דכתיב, dichtiv, יפתח השם לך את אוצרו הטוב את השמים לתת
מטר ארצך בעתו. Yiftach Hashem lecha et otzaro hatov et hashamayim latet
metar artzecha be'ito. God should open up for you his warehouse, the
heavens to give the rain, you know to give the rain in
the right time. מפתח של חיה, Mafteach shel chaya, childbirth, מנלן דכתיב,
menalan dichtiv, ויזכור אלוקים את רחל וישמע אליה אלוקים ויפתח את רחמה.
Vayizkor Elokim et Rachel vayishma eleiha Elokim vayiftach et rachmah. God remembered
רחל, Rachel, God heard her, and opened up her womb. מפתח של
תחיית המתים מנלן דכתיב, Mafteach shel techiyat hameitim menalan dichtiv, the verse
says: וידעתם כי אני השם בפתחי את קברותיכם, Viyadatem ki ani Hashem
b'pitchi et kivroteichem, you'll know that I am God
when I open up your graves. Now, one thing to notice here,
two things to notice. Number one is in all three of these
things it says the verb פותח, poteach, בפתחי, b'pitchi, ויפתח, vayiftach, יפתח.
yiftach. So מפתח, mafteach, the key, exactly is the word in the
verse of פתיחה, pticha, of open. Number two is, I think the
מהרש"א Maharsha asks, why didn't it quote the פסוק pasuk by לאה
Leah where it says God opened up her womb, which occurs earlier
than רחל. Rachel. And he said they wanted a פסוק pasuk where
the word God's name was immediately juxtaposed to the word ויפתח. vayiftach.
And in all these three things it says וישמע אליה אלוקים ויפתח,
vayishma eleiha Elokim vayiftach, right? אני השם בפתחי. Ani Hashem b'pitchi. In
all three of them not only is it the idea that God
opens it up, but it's immediately juxtaposed. And that's the idea, God
directly controls this. There's nothing between God and the opening up. So
the פסוק pasuk by לאה Leah wasn't immediately juxtaposed and they want
to emphasize this is all God's control. So again, the point here
being, I think multiple, number one is that this is, you know,
directly about God's involvement in the Earth. Like if you think about
a שליח, shaliach, an intermediary, you know, there are reasons it doesn't
rain, there's you know, natural
meteorological. meteorological reasons, other explanations, to some degree God is involved, but
that's not the immediate cause. The גמרא Gemara doesn't want you thinking
like that. Right, the גמרא Gemara wants you thinking that these are
things like עיני השם אלוקיך בה, einei Hashem Elokecha bah, like the
פסוק pasuk that was quoted earlier, that God is directly involved in
it. And therefore your sort of prayer to God or your relationship
to God is direct, it has a direct impact, you should interpret
this directly as something coming from God or the absence as directly
a problem between you and God. And that also relates to then
how you respond to God when these things are, when it's going
good and also when it's going bad. So basically the message is
that this is the central way that God sort of or a
central way that God is relating to us on this earth and
that therefore that we connect to God. The presence of it or
the absence, that God is directly involved. That's point number one. Obviously
the rainfall. But then the other two points are the point of
life, right? God brings life into existence, childbirth and the resurrection. And
that obviously evokes the idea that rain is central to our life.
Right? Rain, we need water and we need sustenance and the crops
and so on. And to be seeing all three of these things
as, again, God is directly involved because all of these are directly
about sustaining our life or creating or creating new life or bringing
life or resurrecting. And that just ties into the third point of
the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look. The final point, which is
במערבא אמרי, b'Maarava amrei, in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they say, which
is funny because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is from ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, אמרי, amrei, אף מפתח של פרנסה, af mafte'ach shel parnassah,
even the general like livelihood, not related to rain, דכתיב פותח את
ידך ומשביע לכל חי רצון. d'ksiv pose'ach es yadecha umasbia l'chol chai
ratzon. Okay, although there it doesn't have God's name juxtaposed with פתיחה.
pesicha. רבי יוחנן מאי טעמא לא קחשיב להא, Rabbi Yochanan mai ta'ama
lo k'chashiv l'ha, why isn't he including that? אמר לך גשמים היינו
פרנסה. amar lach geshamim hainu parnassah. It's essentially the same. I mean
if you're an agricultural society, what represents your פרנסה parnassah is גשמים.
geshamim. But of course, by abstracting it to פרנסה parnassah you lose
some of the punch. Right? Because by abstracting it to פרנסה, parnassah,
it's more abstract. God's involved in our
livelihood. Rain is again, it says that כי כאשר ירד הגשם מן
השמים, ki ka'asher yereid hageshem min hashamayim, ושמה לא ישוב, v'shamah lo
yashuv, the same way the rain comes from heaven, my word comes
down. The imagery of the rain, the water
as life, is much more concrete and immediate and felt, and therefore
it doesn't always help to abstract it. There's a power to be
thinking about this as God is directly involved here. Now I want
to say another thing, which is there's another place where we link
גשמים geshamim to תחיית המתים, techiyas hameisim, which is where?
Where else do we link other than the פסוקים pesukim here that
they're in the hands of God? Where do we say it in
שמונה עשרה? Shmoneh Esrei? Right? The whole ברכה bracha אתה גיבור לעולם
ה', Atah Gibbor L'olam Hashem, right, מחיה מתים אתה רב להושיע משיב
הרוח ומוריד הגשם, mechayeh meisim Atah rav l'hoshia mashiv haruach umorid hageshem,
מכלכל חיים בחסד
מחיה מתים ברחמים רבים. m'chalkel chayim b'chesed mechayeh meisim b'rachamim rabbim. So
anyway, it's all linked together. Now this is the point I wanted
to say that Reuven Kimelman says. I mean the normal way of
thinking about it is it's a ברכה bracha of תחיית המתים, techiyas
hameisim, but we somehow abstracted it a little bit to be about
גבורה gevurah and therefore rain also fits there
because it's about life and like we said, like this
מדרש Midrash sort of indicates, it's similar, it's about giving life, so
we'll throw it there as well. But basically it's a ברכה bracha
of
תחיית המתים. techiyas hameisim. What Reuven Kimelman said in an article I
read is he suggests, I'm trying to remember if I'm accurately remembering
and say this, but I think he suggests something along those lines
but like with a twist. He says that by inserting the idea
of גשמים geshamim into that ברכה, bracha, what we're actually doing is
trying to make the idea of תחיית המתים techiyas hameisim more persuasive.
Because if you recognize God's power as bringing down the water, and
what is it like? Like the world looks dead. Things are buried
in the ground. Water comes down and things that were buried in
the ground now sprout to life. So you see in your own
day-to-day existence how the rain that comes from God brings about a
type of
a תחיית המתים techiyas hameisim and therefore that then makes the whole
idea of תחיית המתים techiyas hameisim something that you can really believe
in and relate to and concretizes it. So he actually sort of
sees this as part of making תחיית המתים techiyas hameisim more persuasive,
not just that's why it's sort of being placed here to concretize
that idea. And again, I think that's powerful in the way רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is also bringing these ideas together.
Yes. You said it's all פרק ב' Perek Beis of בראשית. Bereishis.
All of creation sprouts from the ground starting with human beings after
the water. Right.
Excellent. Excellent. Yeah.
There seem to have been some נביאים nevi'im who were given keys.
That's a good question. I'm not going to get into unpacking that.
But the other thing I did want to say about that though
was that yes, these are directly in the hands of God, the
keys, but how do we get God to use. It's because as
I, again, I was reading somebody last night who discusses this, he
says, the מפתח Mafte'ach is the hand of God, but the מפתח
Mafte'ach to the מפתח Mafte'ach is in the hands of humans. Right,
so רחל Rochel cries out and therefore God opens, right, you do
observe the מצוות Mitzvot and therefore God brings the rain. So in
the end, it's in the hands of God, but that's ultimately in
our hands is to and that again gets to the idea that
this is all about our direct relationship with God. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer: מיום טוב
הראשון של חג. mi'yom tov harishon shel chag So you start saying
it on the first day of סוכות Sukkot and רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua says only after the last day. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. רבי
אליעזר מהיכא גמיר לה. Rabbi Eliezer meicheika gmir lah. Where does רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer get the idea that you start saying it on
the first day? מלולב גמר לה Milulav gmar lah from לולב Lulav
which is connected to water as we'll see, ומניסוך המים גמר לה
Uminisuch hamayim gmar lah or from the pouring of water that you
also did on סוכות. Sukkot. So what's the difference? מלולב גמר לה
Milulav gmar lah if he learned out the idea that סוכות Sukkot
is the time of rain from לולב, Lulav, מה לולב ביום אף
הזכרה ביום. Mah lulav bayom af hazkarah bayom. So the same way
לולב Lulav starts the day, the first day of סוכות, Sukkot, you
start saying according to him, משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv haruach umorid
hagashem on the first day but not the night before. או דילמא
מניסוך המים גמר לה O dilma minisuch hamayim gmar lah or maybe
he learns it out from ניסוך המים. Nisuch hamayim. מה ניסוך המים
מאורתא. Mah nisuch hamayim me'orta. But ניסוך המים Nisuch hamayim could in
theory, although we do ניסוך המים Nisuch hamayim in the morning, it
could in theory begin the night before, דאמר מר ומנחתם ונסכיהם אפילו
בלילה. De'amar mar uminchatam veniskeihem afilu balailah. We teach the מנחה Mincha
and their נסכים, Nesachim, that when you bring a מנחה Mincha ונסכיהם
venesachim of a קורבן, Korban, you could do it at night. Now
that's not exactly relevant because that's you bring the קורבן Korban at
day and you can finish it up with the מנחה Mincha and
the נסכים Nesachim at night. But since ניסוך Nisuch pouring libations can
be done at night, so therefore in theory, תוספות Tosafot says it's
again not agreed that this is what the גמרא Gemara means, but
תוספות Tosafot says it means that in theory we could begin the
ניסוך המים Nisuch hamayim at night as well. רש"י Rashi doesn't like
that conclusion. רש"י Rashi just says the process begins at night. You
know we do the whole שמחת בית השואבה Simchat Beit Hasho'eivah at
night. Okay, but anyway if it's ניסוך המים Nisuch hamayim it more
already begins the night before and therefore אף הזכרה מאורתא. Af hazkarah
me'orta. If that's your source, then we should start saying משיב הרוח
Mashiv haruach according to him the night of the first night of
סוכות. Sukkot. תא שמע. Ta shma. So come and hear, דאמר רבי
אבהו. De'amar Rabbi Abbahu. רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu says לא למדה רבי
אליעזר אלא מלולב. Lo lamdah Rabbi Eliezer ella milulav. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer learned it from לולב Lulav so he would only have you
start saying it the first day of סוכות. Sukkot. איכא דאמרי. Ika
de'amri. Some say רבי אבהו גמרא גמיר לה Rabbi Abbahu gemara gmir
lah that he had it as a tradition that that was רבי
אליעזר'ס Rabbi Eliezer's source. ואיכא דאמרי. Ve'ika de'amri. Some say מתניתא שמיע
ליה. Matnita shmi'a leih. He actually had a ברייתא Braita that indicated
this. מאי היא. Mai hi. What's the ברייתא? Braita? דתניא. Detanya. We
taught in the ברייתא. Braita. מאימתי מזכירין על גבורות גשמים. Me'eimatai mazkirin
al gevurot geshamim. When do you mention the rain? רבי אליעזר אומר
משעת נטילת לולב. Rabbi Eliezer omer misha'at netilat lulav. So he's very
explicit. From the time you begin taking לולב. Lulav. רבי יהושע אומר
משעת הנחתו. Rabbi Yehoshua omer misha'at hanachato.
Only after you place it down, only after you're done with the
לולב, Lulav, only starting on שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. אמר רבי אליעזר.
Amar Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said, הוא וארבעה מינים הללו
אינם באים אלא לרצות על המים. Hu ve'arba'ah minim hallalu einam ba'im
ella lirtzot al hamayim.
Look,
the whole idea of the לולב Lulav is that they're coming as
a type of a prayer for the rain. I mean these are
things that grow on the water and we shake it and all
of this. We assume that the idea, I mean you could ask
what is the point of לולב, Lulav, but it's reasonable to assume,
and he assumes, that it's a type of a prayer for rain.
So כשם שארבעה מינים הללו אי אפשר בהם בלא מים. Keshem she'arba'ah
minim hallalu i efshar bahem belo mayim. In the same way that
they need water and they therefore represent the fact that plants depend
on water. כך אי אפשר לעולם בלא
מים. Kach i efshar la'olam belo mayim. The world can't exist without
water. I mean that's what's implicit in our taking of the לולב.
Lulav. We're saying to God, look God, these are living things, they
depend on water, we depend on water. Please make sure that we
have water this coming year. So he says, if you start taking
לולב Lulav you should start saying משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם. Mashiv haruach
umorid hagashem. אמר לו רבי יהושע. Amar lo Rabbi Yehoshua. רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua said to him, והלא גשמים בחג אינן אלא סימן קללה.
Vehalo geshamim bachag einan ella siman klalah. What are you talking about?
If it rains on סוכות Sukkot that's a bad thing. אמר לו
רבי אליעזר. Amar lo Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said back,
אף אני לא אמרתי לשאול אלא להזכיר. Af ani lo amarti lish'ol
ella lehazkir. I agree you don't want it right now. So you
don't ask for it, but you begin mentioning it. You want to
sort of start the process. וכשם שתחיית המתים מזכיר כל השנה כולה.
Ukeshem shetechiyat hametim mazkir kol hashanah kullah.
And the same way you mention תחיית המתים Techiyat hametim which is
what the whole strength of that ברכה Bracha is the whole year,
ואינה אלא בזמנה, Ve'einah ella bizmanah, but that will come in its
right time. כך מזכיר גבורות גשמים כל השנה. Kach mazkir gevurot geshamim
kol hashanah.
You mention them the whole year, ואינן אלא בזמנן, Ve'einan ella bizmanan,
and you only want them in the right time. Now he said,
what do you mean the whole year? I thought you said starting
on the first day of סוכות. Sukkot. So now he's going to
tell you. He said, לפיכך אם בא להזכיר כל השנה כולה מזכיר.
Lefichach im ba lehazkir kol hashanah kullah mazkir.
And therefore I would say yeah, you want to say משיב הרוח
ומוריד הגשם Mashiv haruach umorid hagashem the whole year. Why not?
It's part of recognizing God's power and it's appropriate for תחיית המתים
Techiyat hametim even if it's not the time. Now תוספות Tosafot points
out that there's a difference. He says if you want to say
it the whole year you may, but you are obligated to start
saying it on the first day of סוכות Sukkot when it is
beginning to be the rainy season. So he's saying look, I agree
you don't start asking for it yet
because asking for it is only when you're really ready for it
to come. But because it's now the rainy season you start... mentioning
and mentioning is not the same as asking, because you could really
mention it the whole year if you wanted to. So that fact
that you could do it the whole year makes it clear that
it's not the same as asking, that it's just it's praising God
and God's power and acknowledging God's power and that's what it is.
But so therefore you can do it the whole year, but you're
obligated to do it when it's the appropriate time, when it's the
rainy season. But even when you do it, it doesn't mean that
you're asking for it yet. It means that you're mentioning it because
it's the timeframe, the asking for it will come later. That's Rabbi
Eliezer's position. Let's just see what Rabbi Yehoshua says back. So he
says,
okay, רבי אומר, Rabbi Omer, oh so we don't have Rabbi Yehoshua's
response, so now we have רבי, Rabbi, and רבי Rabbi says a
variation or a defense of Rabbi Yehoshua. רבי אומר, Rabbi Omer, רבי
Rabbi says, אומר אני, Omer Ani, I say, משעה שפוסקין שאילה, mishat
she-poskin she'ila, when you stop asking תן טל ומטר, tein tal u-matar,
you don't say תן טל ומטר tein tal u-matar after the first
day of פסח, Pesach, כך מפסיק להזכירה, kach mafsik lehazkira, you have
to stop saying משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם. Mashiv HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem. So
what רבי Rabbi is saying is, I don't agree with what you
said Rabbi Eliezer, you're not allowed to say משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם
Mashiv HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem during the rest of the year. And therefore
you're not allowed to say it at the beginning of סוכות Sukkot
if it's not the time. I do not believe that you can
have this as a general שבח. shevach. It's very much tied in
to בקשה. bakasha. So again I think that this is like we
said when we began it, this is I think the debate. Rabbi
Eliezer says I am prepared to see this as a general שבח.
shevach. A general שבח shevach in theory you could say the whole
year, you have to say it when it's the season, but in
theory you could say it the whole year, but it's not an
implicit tie-in to asking for it, even when you say it on
סוכות. Sukkot. Whereas רבי Rabbi and Rabbi Yehoshua are saying no, this
is all tied in to תן טל ומטר, tein tal u-matar, you
stop saying it when you stop saying תן טל ומטר, tein tal
u-matar, so when you begin saying it, it's a lead-in to תן
טל ומטר, tein tal u-matar, and therefore you don't start saying it
when it's not yet when you're not yet ready for it. Okay.
And now we have
רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira Omer, בשני בחג
הוא מזכיר, besheni be-chag hu mazkir, agrees to Rabbi Eliezer's idea that
it's tied in to it's in the middle of סוכות, Sukkot, not
at the end. But he says it's only on the second day
of סוכות, Sukkot, and we'll see because he believes that the ניסוך
המים, Nisuch HaMayim, it's tied to the ניסוך המים Nisuch HaMayim and
the ניסוך המים Nisuch HaMayim according to him only began on the
second day of
סוכות. Sukkot. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva Omer, בששי בחג הוא מזכיר,
beshishi be-chag hu mazkir, because Rabbi Akiva also says it's tied into
the ניסוך המים, Nisuch HaMayim, but for him that began on the
sixth of
סוכות. Sukkot. Okay, רבי יהודה משום רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehuda mishum
Rabbi Yehoshua Omer, Rabbi Yehuda in the name of Rabbi Yehoshua says,
and this is Rabbi Yehuda in our משנה, Mishna, העובר לפני התיבה
ביום טוב האחרון של חג, ha-over lifnei ha-teiva be-yom tov ha-acharon shel
chag, that the that on the last day of סוכות, Sukkot, meaning
on שמיני עצרת, Shmini Atzeret, האחרון מזכיר, ha-acharon mazkir, the בעל מוסף
Baal Musaf says it, הראשון אינו מזכיר, ha-rishon eino mazkir, the בעל
שחרית Baal Shacharit does not say it. ביום טוב הראשון של פסח,
be-yom tov ha-rishon shel Pesach, the first day of פסח, Pesach, הראשון
מזכיר, ha-rishon mazkir, האחרון אינו מזכיר, ha-acharon eino mazkir, it's the reverse.
The first guy says it, the בעל שחרית, Baal Shacharit, the בעל
מוסף Baal Musaf already does not say it. Okay, so that's all
the whole range of positions. Let's just read a little bit more
in the גמרא. Gemara. So שפיר קאמר ליה רבי אליעזר לרבי יהושע,
shafir ka'amar lei Rabbi Eliezer le-Rabbi Yehoshua, so Rabbi Eliezer's response to
Rabbi Yehoshua was a good one. So if תחיית המתים techiyat ha-meitim
means when it's the right time, so why can't משיב הרוח ומוריד
הגשם Mashiv HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem mean when it's the right time? So
אמר לך רבי יהושע, amar lecha Rabbi Yehoshua, Rabbi Yehoshua will say
back to you, no. בשלמא תחיית המתים מזכיר דכל יומא זמניה הוא,
bishlama techiyat ha-meitim mazkir de-chol yoma zmanei hu, we you know we'd
love to have תחיית המתים techiyat ha-meitim any day, so it might
not come until it's the right time, but any day we're ready
for it. אלא גשמים, ela geshamim, but rain, כל אימת דאתי זמנייהו?
kol eimat de-ati zmanaihu? Do you think anytime it rains would be
a good thing? והתנן, ve-hatnan, we teach later,
יצא ניסן וירדו גשמים סימן קללה הן, yatza Nisan ve-yardu geshamim siman
klala hein, it's bad to have rain in the wrong time. שנאמר,
she-ne'emar, הלא קציר חטים היום? halo katzir chitim hayom? So and the
פסוק pasuk sort of indicates that it's not the time for rain.
So therefore it's an obvious difference. תחיית המתים techiyat ha-meitim we want
it anytime. Rain, even if you're mentioning God's גבורה, gevura, you actually
don't want it certain times and therefore you should not be mentioning
it. Okay, so there is this debate but again I think it's
link anchored in the issue of whether you think משיב הרוח ומוריד
הגשם Mashiv HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem is fundamentally שבח shevach or is it
ultimately just a tie-in and a lead-in to תן טל ומטר לברכה.
tein tal u-matar livracha. So tomorrow we'll unpack the issue about second
day or sixth day, but I want to say one other final
point before we end which is the idea and I'll get I'll
say this again, but the idea of going from פסח Pesach through
סוכות Sukkot without saying it. You know I was reading an article
last night by this person Rabbi Dov Berkowitz, not I think it's
not the same as Rabbi Eliezer Berkowitz, Rabbi Eliyahu who was נפטר
niftar a good number of years ago. Anyway Rabbi Dov Berkowitz who
points out like the interesting thing again in terms of like the
religious mindset. He says think about it. All the times we have
ימים טובים, yamim tovim, we don't have משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם. Mashiv
HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem. We only have משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv HaRuach
uMorid HaGeshem during like the dead time of the year, the time
when there's no ימים טובים, yamim tovim, right? You're like I mean
okay you get it at the very end you know you get
it at the very Very last day of, very end of שמיני
עצרת, Shmini Atzeret, at the very beginning, but ultimately it's during the
time when there's no ימים טובים. Yomim Tovim. And he sort of
says look, he says during the period of the ימים טובים Yomim
Tovim from ניסן Nisan through סוכות, Succot, that's the time when you
are out and working in the fields, you're harvesting, you know, you're
plowing, you're planting, or whatever, that's when you're doing all of your
human activity. And therefore and the one of the themes of the
חגים Chagim is to direct that human activity and that sort of
bringing the stuff in and direct it to God, right? So to
acknowledge, you know, that you know, that it's you know that פסח
Pesach is the time of barley and שבועות Shavuot is the time
of wheat and the time of ביכורים Bikkurim and you bring the
ביכורים Bikkurim and you say God gave me these things and סוכות
Succot you bring in all the harvest and ושמחת לפני ה' אלוקיך.
Vesamachta Lefanei Hashem Elokecha. So it's to take all of that human
endeavor and to put it in a religious context and sort of
like to acknowledge God, and that's all achieved by the חגים. Chagim.
Says in the period from סוכות Succot to פסח Pesach there's very
little human endeavor. You basically have done the planting and now you're
just waiting for the rain, right? So it's basically it's not like
oh I'm going to think it's all my doing, it's actually a
time period of the year where you're very much are not doing
much and are acknowledging it's all dependent on God. So therefore he
says so that gets filled, that sort of acknowledgement with the משיב
הרוח ומוריד הגשם, Mashiv haruach umorid hagashem, you know, sort of with
that acknowledgement like it's all about prayer and waiting for God to
sort of you know to do God's part or calling on God,
but that's sort of the religious reality there whereas on the other
time it's very much your activity and then you have to sort
of take that activity and translate it in a way that acknowledges
God, so you know you bring the ביכורים, Bikkurim, you share with
your harvest to the עני, Ani, the גר, Ger, and the יתום,
Yatom, you know, you take the לולב Lulav and the אתרוג Etrog
ושמחת לפני ה' אלוקיך, Vesamachta Lefanei Hashem Elokecha, so you take that
activity and you give to you know and you direct it towards
God, whereas here it's much more of a passive period and a
period of like just sort of like more silent dependency where it
translates in terms of prayer and you know waiting for God for
the rains to come. So I think that's like a very profound,
what, it's out of our hands. So I think that was really
powerful for me to think about like the different, you know, sort
of ways of being during the different times of the year and
the different type of like religious response that's appropriate. Okay so to
be continued tomorrow.